<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>pablo peñarroja millán</title>
 <link href="http://soybin.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://soybin.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2020-06-19T19:59:29+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://soybin.github.io/</id>
 <author>
   <name>pablo peñarroja millán</name>
   <email>soybinary@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>raymarching the geometry & pathtracing the scene</title>
	 <link href="https://soybin.github.io/articles/2020/04/01/raymarching.html"/>
   <updated>2020-04-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
	 <id>http://soybin.github.io/articles/2020/04/01/raymarching</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;!---[*fractal rendered with idyll using raymarching and path tracing*](/images/idyll/first.png){:width=&quot;100%&quot;}---&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;raymarching-the-geometry--pathtracing-the-scene&quot;&gt;raymarching the geometry &amp;amp; pathtracing the scene&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preamble&quot;&gt;preamble&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I’ll superficially explain and reflect on the logic behind the rendering pipeline that I came up with when developing  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cFykbtJmg4A&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;idyll&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a fractal engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;definitions&quot;&gt;definitions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ray&lt;/em&gt;: simple structure composed of two \(n\) dimensional vectors: an &lt;strong&gt;origin&lt;/strong&gt; vector, which indicates at which point in space the ray originates, and a unit &lt;strong&gt;direction&lt;/strong&gt; vector, which denotes the direction in which the ray will move.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Geometry&lt;/em&gt;: any independent model, shape or object present in the scene.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scene&lt;/em&gt;: \(n\) dimensional space in which the geometry is represented.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;raymarching&quot;&gt;raymarching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raymarching is simply an algorithm used to interpret a scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The algorithm itself doesn’t compute lighting, shadowing nor reflections on its own, it rather gives you information about whether a ray emitted from a pixel does or doesn’t intersects the surface of any geometry in the scene. In other words, it calculates the depth of the scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;distance-estimators&quot;&gt;distance estimators&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you’re working on a 3-dimensional space, &lt;em&gt;in order to perform raymarching, you need a function that tells you how far away is any given point in space from the closest point to the surface of the geometry&lt;/em&gt;. That’s called a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;distance estimator&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, DE from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most basic DE functions represent primitive objects, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iquilezles.org/www/articles/distfunctions/distfunctions.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a fantastic resource by Íñigo Quílez on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, here you can see the DE function for a sphere \(sphereDE\), where \(P\) is the point in space that you’re calculating how far apart from the sphere it is, and \(S\) is the scale of the sphere (assuming the sphere is located at the origin of coordinates):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[ sphereDE(P, S) = length(P) - S\]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;double sphereDE(vector3 P, double S) {
	return length(P) - S;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-to-do-with-a-de&quot;&gt;what to do with a DE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Once you know how far away from something you are, you know you can safely move that distance in any direction, without having to worry about hitting that object.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let a camera be placed anywhere in your scene with a distance of 10 meters from the origin of coordinates (0, 0, 0), and looking towards it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let a ray have its origin (ori) at the position of the camera in your scene, and give it a direction (dir) towards the center of coordinates.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let a variable total distance (tDist) represent how far away has the ray moved from its origin, and it’ll be initialized to zero.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, calculate the DE from the point O + D * D’ (the origin of the ray plus the direction of the ray times the distance the ray moved).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then you can safely &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;march&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; the ray by the distance returned by the DE function, which means you can add DE(O + D * D’) to D.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Repeat this process until DE(ori + dir * tDist) returns a value smaller than a certain arbitrary threshold (1e-4 for example), which means that the ray is close enough to the surface of the geometry for it to be considered an intersection. Obviously the ray won’t get to hit the geometry itself because of Zeno’s paradox, so it’s an estimation, hence the name distance estimator.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process should be computed for each pixel on the screen, and it’ll provide an accurate interpretation of the model, no matter how complex the distance estimator may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest c++ style code would look something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;// distance threshold
const double MIN_DISTANCE = 1e-4;

/*
 * the maximum number of steps allowed. 
 * if this amount of steps, 'raymarch'
 * will return 0.0
 */
const int MAX_STEP = 64;
 
double raymarch(vector3 ori, vector3 dir) {
	double tDist = 0.0;
	int i;
	for (i = 0; i &amp;lt; MAX_STEP; ++i) {
		double curDist = sphereDE(ori + dir * tDist);
		// in case the threshold is reached
		if (curDist &amp;lt; MIN_DISTANCE) {
			break;
		}
		// else, add the marched distance
		// to the distance variable
		tDist += curDist;
	}
	return 1.0 - (double)i / (double)MAX_STEP;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very simple implementation, and if you were to use the returned value from this function as the value for the three color channels of each pixel, you would get a black and white image with some very obvious banding artifacts (since we’re deriving the return value from two integers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ray-direction&quot;&gt;ray direction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve skipped over this until now, because it’s not vital to conceptually understanding raymarching. However, it is a very important implementation detail in most cases. The following, is an example of a formula for calculating the direction that each pixel’s ray \(rayDirection(P_x, P_y)\) should follow, given a desired field of view \(fov\) in radians:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the constant \(P_x\) be equal to the pixel x-coordinate on your screen.&lt;br /&gt;
Let the constant \(P_y\) be equal to the pixel y-coordinate on your screen.&lt;br /&gt;
Let the constant \(width\) be equal to your screen’s width in pixels.&lt;br /&gt;
Let the constant \(height\) be equal to your screen’s height in pixels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[rayDirection(P_x, P_y) = [x, y, -z]\]
\[x = P_x + 0.5 - \frac{width}{2}\]
\[y = P_y + 0.5 - \frac{height}{2}\]
\[z = \frac{height}{tan(\frac{fov}{2})}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This formula applies to most physically based rendering (pbr) techniques, and the implementation itself is very straighforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;real-world-usage&quot;&gt;real world usage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As long as you can derive a function that, for any given point in 3d space, returns its distance from the closest point to any geometry in the scene, you can render pretty much anything with a great performance. Adding dynamic lighting, shadowing, occlusion and surface color would have a very low computational cost. Even changing the geometry’s scale, position and rotation. Anything is valid, because everything is dynamic and computed in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raymarching is not mainstream in the videogame industry, the reason for this is that you &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; a DE function, and in order for it to run in real time, all of it should to be computed in a fragment shader on the GPU side. When you have a world with hundreds of independent entities interacting with each other, materials to be computed, and very specific and complex geometrical shapes, it becomes counterproductive to have an efficient DE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, whenever you have an accurate DE, you can efficiently compute your scene using raymarching. This makes raymarching the ideal method to render complex mathematical models, such as fractals or combinations of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pathtracing&quot;&gt;pathtracing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pathtracing is a rendering technique derived from raytracing. We’ll discuss the differences between this two terms later in this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two important constants to define when implementing a pathtracing algorithm: the samples per pixel, and the bounces per ray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea behind pathtracing is to &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;iteratively integrate most of the light arriving to a point in the surface of the geometry&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, so that the image looks as real as possible.
To visualize it, this is the pseudocode for a very basic pathtracing algorithm (only Lambertian reflection):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;// number of samples per pixel
const int SAMPLES = 256

// maximum number of allowed ray bounces
const double BOUNCES = 8;

// probability of ray reflection
const double PROB = 1/PI;

// pathtracing recursively
color pathtrace (ray r, int bounces) {
	// in the ray missed
	if (!r.hit) return color(0.0);

	// in case we reached max number of bounces
	if (bounces == BOUNCES) return color(0.0);

	// get ray normal
	vector3 rayNormal = calculateNormal(r.origin, r.direction)

	// get current new ray origin
	vector3 newOrigin = r.origin + r.length * r.direction;

	// get random unit vector in the hemisphere
	// of the normal, so that the ray can bounce off
	vector3 newDir = getHemisphereRandom(rayNormal)

	// get color at the intersected point
	color color = getWorldColor(r.origin)

	// bidirectional reflectance distribution function
	double ct = dot(newDir, rayNormal)
	color brdf = r.hitReflectance / PI;

	ray newRay = {newOrigin, newDir}

	color nextBounce = pathtrace(newRay, bounces + 1);

	// this is where the integration of
	// the lighting along the different
	// intersection points of the ray
	// happens
	return color + (brdf * nextBounce * ct / PROB);
}

// iterate through every pixel in the screen
for (y in height) {
	for (x in width) {
		// get ray's direction and origin
		vector3 direction = rayDirection(x, y)
		vector3 origin = {0, 0, 10.0}
		// variable storing color
		color totalColor = {0.0, 0.0, 0.0}
		// iterate for every sample and add to color
		for (sample in SAMPLES) {
			totalColor += pathtrace(origin, direction, 0);
		}
	}
	color /= samples;
	pixels[y][x] = color;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s happening here is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iterate through every pixel in the screen or image.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~ Compute the ray’s origin and direction from the pixel coordinates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~ Iterate through every sample.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~ ~ Add the return value of the function ‘pathtrace’, which randomly computes a possible value for that ray, to the ‘totalColor’ variable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~ Divide the ‘totalColor’ variable by the number of samples to get the average value for all of the samples.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~ Set the pixel with ‘x’ and ‘y’ coordinates to the ‘totalColor’ variable value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a high enough value for the samples and bounces variable, you can get very photorealistic images using path tracing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;disambiguation&quot;&gt;disambiguation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re reading this, chances are you’ve heard of raytracing, and it’s no coincidence raytracing, raymarching and pathtracing sound familiar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three of these PBR (physically based rendering) algorithms have something in common: &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;they all use raycasting to understand a scene’s geometry&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, but what each one of this algorithms accomplishes, and the way they operate is different from one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can think of raytracing as a complete method that calculates both the point of intersection and the behaviour of the ray after the intersection. Whereas raymarching only computes the point of intersection, and pathtracing only computes the behaviour of the ray after the intersection.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though you might think that raytracing is the union of raymarching and pathtracing, that’s not the case, because the way they carry out both calculating the point intersection and the behaviour of the ray afterwards, greatly differs from one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;raymarching-and-raytracing&quot;&gt;raymarching and raytracing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most notorious difference between raymarching and raytracing is the following:&lt;br /&gt;
In raymarching, the intersection with the scene’s geomtry is computed using a distance estimator, as we’ve recently seen. While as in raytracing, the intersection is analitically computed, and you don’t require a DE. This makes raytracing more suitable for games, although it’s still a very expensive technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pathtracing-and-raytracing&quot;&gt;pathtracing and raytracing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of pathtracing is achieving a similar result to the original raytracing technique but with less computation.
Pathtracing and raytracing both are physically based rendering (PBR) techniques, both are expensive, and both represent reality with very high fidelity.&lt;br /&gt;
Both techniques are fundamentally similar, but their biggest difference is how a ray bounce is determined.
You could argue which one looks better, but at the end of the day, that’s subjective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;union-of-raymarching-and-pathtracing&quot;&gt;union of raymarching and pathtracing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you can see how raymarching and pathtracing can be complementary to each other, making for a solid rendering pipeline:&lt;br /&gt;
With raymarching, you can check whether a ray intersects the geometry or not, and where. Then, you can use pathtracing to integrate the global illumination at the point of intersection between the surface of the geometry and the marched ray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pathtracing computes the lighting, but doesn’t compute the point of intersection with the geometry. On the other hand, raymarching computes the point of intersection with the geometry, but doesn’t compute lighting. This makes the union of these two techniques ideal to render DE functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;thank-you-for-reading-and-contact-me-if-you-have-any-questions-d&quot;&gt;thank you for reading, and contact me if you have any questions :D&lt;/h5&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>on open source</title>
	 <link href="https://soybin.github.io/thoughts/2020/06/15/on-open-source.html"/>
   <updated>2020-06-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
	 <id>http://soybin.github.io/thoughts/2020/06/15/on-open-source</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;it is very cool indeed&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
</feed>
